Guide to the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company Records, 1860-1999 AIS.1982.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company Records
1860-1999
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroad Company
AIS.1982.23
924 Linear Feet (688 records boxes, 14 manuscript boxes, 5 tubes, 1 flat file folder, 16 oversized items, 28 oversized map folders, 31 map rolls and 18 filing cabinet drawers)
The Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company Records document the many facets of the management and operation of the railroad company throughout its long history, mainly from the 1860s through 1999. Digital reproductions of selected photographic images are available online.
History
The Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad (P&LE) began operation in 1879 after the 1878 consolidation with the Youngstown & Pittsburgh Railroad Company. Headquartered in Pittsburgh, Pa., the P&LE line began as a single track railroad connecting Pittsburgh to Youngstown, Ohio. The railroad began its affiliation with the New York Central System in 1883 and, by 1890, was one of the principle rail routes in the eastern United States. Financed in part by the Harmony Society, a communal religious sect located just north of Pittsburgh in Economy, Pa., and in part by William Henry Vanderbilt's Lake Shore & Michigan Southern Railway, the P&LE had extended south to Connellsville, Pa., and handled six times the amount of freight it had in 1880, earning its nickname, the "Little Giant."
The P&LE continued to progress into the twentieth century thanks, in part, to the advances in railroad technology. The development of all-steel cars made it possible to carry a load of up to 50-tons. Additionally, advancements made in train brakes through the Westinghouse air brake system and automatic couplers, allowed P&LE trains to run safely at faster speeds and carry heavier coal loads.
The P&LE also operated as a passenger line. Beginning with its first passenger train in February 1879, the railroad became a heavily used line by travelers and commuters. Although passenger trips were relatively small, the average trip was around 20 miles. Until 1941, the passenger trains accounted for one-half the miles of the freight trains. However, the rise of popularity of motor trucks, private cars, and buses led to the eventual decline of train travel. By the mid-1970s, only one commuter train remained on the P&LE line.
While the early 1970s brought a decline in passenger travel, the freight lines continued to grow. In 1976, following the 1970 bankruptcy of the Penn Central System, the railroad obtained trackage rights over former Penn Central lines to Ashtabula Harbor, Oh., located on Lake Erie and through Sharon to Shenango, Pa. The railroad was purchased by CSX Transportation in 1993.
Arrangement
The collection was inventoried by several graduate students in the fall of 2010 which produced a box-level inventory. An intellectual arrangement was then created based on each individual railroad line that comprised the P&LE. The corresponding box information is included, but note that the material is loosely arranged in the boxes and in no significant order. The physical arrangement is imprecise and uncontrolled because up to this point, no processing has been done to any part of this collection other than the photographs. Considering that a number of people worked to create this box inventory and the scale of this collection is so large, the contents may not be exactly what the finding aid claims them to be.
Each series represents the various railroad lines found within the overall company records of the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad, followed by non-manuscript materials. Five subseries exist within the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad series, giving a rough outline of the large amount of materials generated by the operation of the railroad.
Series I. Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad, 1908-1980s
Series II. Mahoning State Line Railroad, 1895-1980
Series III. Monongahela Connecting Railroad, 1864-1989
Series IV. Montour Railroad, 1900-1956
Series V. New York Central System, 1905-1965
Series VI. Pittsburgh, Chartiers & Youghiogheny Railroad, 1898-1995
Series VII. Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad, 1860-1994
Subseries 1. Engineering, 1850-1944
Subseries 2. Financial, 1850-1994
Subseries 3. General Operations, 1883-1982
Subseries 4. Labor, 1850-1994
Subseries 5. Legal, 1850-1994
Series VIII. Pittsburgh, Lisbon & Western Railroad, 1925-1945
Series IX. Pittsburgh, McKeesport & Youghiogheny Railroad, 1870-1960
Series X. Youngstown & Southern Railroad, 1900-1956
Series XI. Training Material, 1970s-1980s
Series XII. Audio-Visual Materials
Series XIII. Oversize, 1913-1981
Series XIV. Maps, Drawings and Plans, 1872-1990
Scope and Content Notes
The Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company Records document the management and operation of the company throughout its long history, from around 1850 to 1999. These materials contain information about Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad (P&LE), as well as the various branch lines that, along with P&LE, were controlled by the New York Central Railroad System from 1883 until 1968, and later by Penn Central from 1968 until 1970. Regardless of the large number of materials, this is not a complete record of P&LE history, or of its subsidiaries.
The manuscript material includes a large number of bound ledgers of meeting minutes, statistics, operational logs, and reports. Many ledgers contain letter or telegraph correspondence between personnel, external companies, subsidiaries, and employees. Employee records comprise card indexes, files, and folders of terminated, retired, furloughed, and deceased employees as well as applications, recommendations, rates of pay, sick and vacation time, and union agreements. Legal documents consist of claims and grievances against P&LE by employees, companies, cities, and citizens; articles of agreement concerning the lease of equipment, land, and tracks; and contracts between P&LE, its subsidiaries and associate companies. Publications scattered throughout the collection include federal regulations (many of the Interstate Commerce Commission), company safety policy and handbooks, national railroad magazines, and multi-railroad agreements. Bulletins and notices were distributed within the company and sometimes are referred to as 'pink sheets.' There is also a substantial presence of blueprints of buildings and tracks and schematics for equipment and machinery.
The collection contains over two thousand feet of 16mm motion picture film depicting railroad work crews in the 1930s, various construction projects, a parade of boats on the Monongahela River, and safety and training procedures. Audio cassettes relate to personal safety of employees and the operation of certain railroad equipment. Slides depict safety training exercises and methods, hazardous materials, and other standard safety practices. The film, cassettes, and slides are noted in the Training Materials series. Only the Photographs series in this collection has been processed. The remaining materials have been housed in records boxes, manuscript boxes, filing cabinets, or paper wrappings and still comprise their original folders or none at all. All materials are available for on-site review.
Acquisition Information
The first accession was a gift of Martha E. Ecton in 1982; the second accession was a gift of Jack Polaritz in 1998.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company Records, 1850-1999, AIS.1982.23, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
Due to some records that contain private information (e.g., employee cards), access to portions of the collection requires a signed confidentiality agreement. Please contact the Archives Service Center for more information.
Related Material
Jack Polaritz Collection of the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad, AIS.1998.41, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Jack Polaritz Railroad Collection, AIS.1998.42, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Jack Polartiz Collection of Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Photographs, AIS.1998.54, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Existence and Location of Originals
Digital reproductions of portions of the photographic images are available electronically at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/pittsburgh-lake-erie-railroad-company-records.
Separated Material
Boxes containing photographs are located in the Media Storage Room at the Archives Service Center. A number of employee and train indexes are housed in filing cabinets in the West Wing of the Archives Service Center.
Bibliography
McLean, Harold H. Pittsburgh and Lake Erie R.R. San Marino, CA: Golden West Books, 1980.
McKeesport (Pa.); Photographs; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Ashtabula (Ohio); Gateway Yard (Youngstown, Ohio); Engineering drawings -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County.; Collective labor agreements -- Transport workers -- United States; Business and Industry; Coke industry -- Pennsylvania; Labor; Accident reports; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Railroad equipment industry -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Railroad engineering; Railroad companies -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Records and correspondence; Railroad accidents -- Investigation -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Lake Erie and Ohio River Canal (Ohio and Pa.: Proposed); Transportation; Ledgers (Account books); Legal documents -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh.; Locomotive industry -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; McKees Rocks (Pa.); Coal mines and mining -- Pennsylvania; Coal trade -- Pennsylvania; Neville Island (Pa.); Transportation -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; Youngstown (Ohio); Youngstown & Southern Railway; Pittsburgh Lisbon & Western Railroad; Aliquippa & Southern Railroad Company.; Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad Company.; Mahoning State Line Railroad Company; Montour Railroad Company; New York Central Railroad Company; Pittsburgh, Chartiers and Youghiogheny Railway Company; Penn Central Transportation Company; Jones & Laughlin Steel Corporation; Monongahela Connecting Railroad Company; Pennsylvania Railroad; ConRail; MCCune, Frank; Mahoning, Beaver and Ellwood Railroad Company; Waynesburg Southern Railroad; Little Kanawha Syndicate; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission
- Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad, 1908-1980s; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  On December 14, 1907, the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad purchased one-half interest in the Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad, a Youngstown switching line.
  This series has a number of documents related to this railroad line that show Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad's daily operations from its purchase date in 1907 through 1979. The Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad series, dating 1908-1980s, contains reports, blueprints, employee records, and contracts. The information is by no means a complete record of this particular line.
  - Crossings, bridges, and arches, 1908 (Box 162)
  - Engineering Department - Information pertaining to the construction of the Lake Erie & Eastern Railroad, 1950s (Box 199)
  - Engineering Department - Connellsville Western Maryland abandonments, Detroit Edison Trains, Montour Railroad champion terminal study, Penn Central use of Lake Erie & Eastern, Walford Branch, Ohio River Branch, 1980s (Box 221)
  - Engineering Department - Bids regarding contracts for roadside structures, special file on Duquesne contracting co., Right of Way Lake Erie & Eastern, 1910-1950s (Box 230)
  - Engineering Department - Information Pertaining to the construction of the LE&E RR: 1662 (Special File - Duquesne Contr. Co and bids on grading and concrete between Cedar St and Division Streets), 1662 (LE&E RR main file surveying tracks), 1662-A-2-5 (LE&E roadbed and track), 1662-B (Vacation of streets and crossings from 1905), Early 1900s (Box 235)
  - Microfilmed minute books, 1912-1959 (Box 374)
  - Annual reports of Lake Erie & Eastern, Youngstown & Southern, Mahoning State Line, and Montour Railroads, 1949-1979 (Box 377)
  - Information pertaining to the construction of the LE&E railroad; connection to Ohio Works, Carnegie Steel; accounts and payroll of LE&E railroad, 1914-1944 (Box 421)
  - Personal injury summary cards of Montour Railroad employees; LE&E records book; notes on cross sections; LE&E and PL&E crossing agreements, 1922-1965 (Box 540)
- Mahoning State Line Railroad, 1895-1980; II.
  Incorporated on August 10, 1891, the Mahoning State Line Railroad was opened January 1, 1895. The line was built by the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company under agreement with the Lake Shore & Michigan Southern Railway Company and the New York, Lake Erie & Western Railroad Company in order to reach the limestone district of western Pennsylvania and eastern Ohio. Starting on November 26, 1895, the line was leased to the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie Railroad Company for a 99-year term.
  This series contains a small number of documents mixed in with other railroad documents, such as studies, journal entries, annual reports, and agreements. The information stretches from 1895 to 1980.
  - Mahoning State Line Journal Entries (1925-79), Mahoning State Line General Ledger (1895-1944), ICC Annual reports (1972-77), 1895-1977 (Box 148)
  - Annual reports of the Pittsburgh & Lake Erie, Mahoning State Line, Monongahela Connecting, and Beaver & Ellwood railroads, 1901-1909 (Box 371)
  - Annual reports of Lake Erie & Eastern, Youngstown & Southern, Mahoning State Line, and Montour railroads, 1949-1979 (Box 377)
  - Ohio and Pennsylvania new legislation concerning P&LE, engineering dept.; B&O's use of tracks-McKeesport to Port Vue; correspondence on grade crossings and right of way with Lake Erie Limestone Co.; agreements with Republic Steel Company and Mahoning State Line Railroad, 1923-1955 (Box 454b)
  - Pittsburgh & Lake Erie and Monongahela Connecting Railroad: Office of industrial engineering operations; iron ore movements; hopper and gondola studies; correspondence concerning Montour Junction auto ramp; Mahoning State Line Railroad study; Dravo Stone proposal, 1968-1980 (Box 476)
- Monongahela Connecting Railroad, 1864-1919; III.
  The Monongahela Connecting Railroad was a small industrial railroad and subsidiary of the Jones & Laughlin Steel Company. Much of its work was for its parent company, but it also served other industries along the line. It may be best known by its hot metal bridge, which was used to carry molten iron across the Monongahela River from J&L's Eliza Furnaces to the Bessemer converters and rolling mills at J&L's South Side facility. The railroad was also a dieselization pioneer, buying many early diesel locomotives from Alco, General Electric and other manufacturers.
  The Monongahela Connecting Railroad series includes litigation, reports, correspondence, and daily operational materials from 1870 to 1991. Documentation in this collection is the most complete of any of the subsidiaries and provides a complete picture of the operations of this line from its beginning with only some overlap with other railroads. Many of the ledgers pertaining to this railroad contains correspondence between Frank McCune, the General Superintendent of the Monongahela Connecting Railroad (early 1900s), and other companies and employees. Unlike some of the other material found in this collection, this series offers an important perspective because it documents railroad communications from the top down.
  - Law Dept - Delaware & Hudson Railway Bankruptcy, CSX vs. Monongahela Railroad, Burlington Northern Railroad Co. vs. P&LE, Norfolk Western vs. P&LE, 1970s-1980s (Box 110)
  - Abandonment of Track in Marion W. Va, Acquisition of Trackage rights; Pennsylvania Railroad correspondence, 1960s (Box 158)
  - Correspondence of General Manager concerning general railroad operations, 1909-1917 (Box 261)
  - Correspondence, engine coal consumption statistics, orders, financial statements of monthly savings, 1909-1917 (Box 262)
  - Correspondence, Semi-Annual Report ending Dec 18 1918, orders, National Safety Contest and Accidents on Steam Railroads in Pa., 1905-1918 (Box 263)
  - Correspondence and other files, 1905-1918 (Box 264)
  - All matters pertaining to: File 2 (Slag, Refuse, Rubbish, Ashes), File 3 (Limestone, Ore, Coke, Scrap), File 8 (Per Diem, Demurrage, Coal, Police Department), File 9 (Applications, Dismissals, Promotions, Pittsburgh Mercantile Order, Salaries), 1912-1914 (Box 265)
  - Semi-annual report, correspondence, matters pertaining to Car Dept. (cars of all descriptions, ladles, new equipment, repairs, improper loadings, overloading), matters pertaining to Buildings (office, shops, yard offices, doctor's offices, watchmen's shanties, towers, switchmen's buildings), matters pertaining to limestone, ore, coke, scrap, 1905-1918 (Box 266)
  - Correspondence regarding car weight data, expense reports, General Superintendent's ledgers, 1905-1918 (Box 267)
  - General Superintendent McCune's correspondence concerning crew hour notices, general operations, 1908-1917 (Box 268-269)
  - General Superintendent McCune's correspondence; engineering files concerning payrolls, hospital reports, fatalities, liability, accident reports, safety reports of Jones & Laughlin; Pennsylvania Railroad freight tariff books, 1908-1917 (Box 270)
  - Operating department - correspondence, annual reports, accounts with other railroads, trackage payments, bills and statements, situation reports and special reports, 1917-1918 (Box 271-273)
  - Train Orders Ledgers, Henderson Coal Company, Citizens Water Company, Law Department Correspondence, 1925-1975 (Box 274)
  - Law Department Correspondence, Agreement between Coraopolis and MCRR to add tracks and re-route road, Law office files, 1925-1950s (Box 275)
  - Train and Engineers Daily Call Sheets, Late 1970s (Box 276)
  - Train Clerks correspondence (half sheets), General Manager Letters, Record of Crews Called, cars ledgers; all files pertaining to limestone ore, coke, and scrap, 1914-1990s (Box 277)
  - Correspondence of John L. Moore, purchasing, paymaster, assistant secretary, 1905-1915 (Box 278)
  - Correspondence pertaining to engines, roundhouses, sand house, pan stocks, coal situations, ash pits. Store room department: supplies, material of all description, water, 1914 (Box 279a-280)
  - Correspondence; motive power dept (engines, roundhouse, sandhouse, etc) Store Room Dept., 1918 (Box 281)
  - Correspondence, records of locomotive maintenance, American Railway Circulars, Bulletins, letters pertaining to safety, employee matters, safety inspections, dumps and scrap, utilities, photograph, 1926-1931 (Box 282)
  - Correspondence, construction and maintenance, accident reports, blueprints, Nordberg, Adzing, machine, parts catalogue, purchase orders, 1898-1955 (Box 283a-283b)
  - Correspondence of maintenance, payment records, 1913-1918 (Box 284)
  - Internal memos, steam crane use, product brochures, safety signs, vendor correspondence, daily gondola interchange log, 1906-1914 (Box 290)
  - Frank McCune regarding repairs, accident reports, labor, vendor brochures. Two indexes (07/08): bills, deliveries, job assignments, construction, internal memos. Yearly reports (1907-08), 1906-1923 (Box 291)
  - Correspondence on car maintenance, damages, rentals, and inspections, coal analyses, records of water and waste treatment, and expense reports, 1910-1931 (Box 292a)
  - Correspondence of Frank McCune, matters of motive power department, store room department, and of connecting companies, 1908-1910 (Box 292b)
  - Frank McCune's correspondence concerning repairs, bill, employee affairs, 1905-1913 (Box 293)
  - Correspondence on committee of Unloading Cars reports, reports on empty cars, data, inventory; Pittsburgh Car Service Association correspondence on budgets, expenses, steel company, 1905-1907 (Box 294a)
  - Crane and engine, pilot changes, expenses, account books, medical department; steel company reports and correspondence; employee passes, car reports, data and budgets; steel storage; repairs and engineering; A&L correspondence of purchasing agent, auditor, paymaster regarding inventory and budgeting, 1912-1915 (Box 294b-294c)
  - McCune correspondence: cargo, derailments, general business, cars, labor, building maintenance, track repairs, 1903-1912 (Box 295a-295b)
  - Correspondence regarding freight movement, electrical department, notices, passes, telephones, material inventory monthly reports, material orders, railway publications, 1908-1930 (Box 337a)
  - Track scale records, matters pertaining to slag (granulated & hot), refuse, rubbish, ashes; correspondence concerning locomotives, parts, other matters; miscellaneous correspondence of Frank McCune, superintendent; payment records, 1907-1918 (Box 337b)
  - Frank McCune correspondence with employees regarding applications, dismissals, promotions, salaries, accidents; matters of tracks, bridges, trestles, right of way, and supplies; transportation department matters, 1900-1930 (Box 339a)
  - Matters of car department (ladles, new equipment, repairs, improper loadings, overloading) and buildings; various correspondence of Frank McCune, General Manager, 1910-1920 (Box 339b)
  - Matters of motive power department (engines, round house, sand house, pen stocks, coal stations, ash pits), store room department (supplies, materials, water); M. of W. department (tracks, bridges trestles, right of way, M. of W. supplies); reports on bills, statements, situation reports; matters of per diem, demurrage, coal, police department; blank forms, 1913-1914 (Box 340a)
  - Matters of transportation department (movement of cars, etc); matters of car department and buildings; transportation matters involving Allegheny Regional Association advisory board; blank forms, 1907-1930 (Box 340b)
  - Indexes which contain notices to general manager Frank McCune concerning scales tested, contents of cars, shipping notices, and train delay notices, 1908-1918 (Box 341)
  - Correspondence pertaining to coal, ore, and slag, car movements, matters of employees (applications, dismissal, promotions, salaries, accidents, bonds), transportation, movement of cars, letters to yardmasters, trainmen, 1904-1921 (Box 343-344a)
  - Circulars, bulletins; correspondence pertaining to coal, cars (movements, damages, cleanings, inspections), connecting lines, and J&L Steel; Code of Rules; employee files; reports on yardmasters and relief crews, 1907-1931 (Box 344b)
  - Indexes containing notices to GM McCune concerning new car construction, car deliveries, cargo reports from the Southside Department, car delays, labor distribution reports, 1905-1909 (Box 345a-345b)
  - Matters pertaining to limestone, coke, ore, scrap; bills, statements, and other reports; correspondence of transportation employees (yardmasters, trainmen, etc) and of electrical department, 1909-1911 (Box 346a)
  - Indexes containing bills, statements, notices pertaining new equipment, repairs, inspection reports, delivery notices, coal delivery reports -- most directed to McCune, 1912-1914 (Box 347a)
  - Indexes containing notices concerning construction, transportation, engine use, maintenance, and repairs. Reports of cargo loaded in cars, movement of cars, delays, notices to yardmasters and trainmen, directed toward McCune, 1909-1914 (Box 347b-347c)
  - J&L shipment statements; matters of electrical department; correspondence about employees; matters of crane and engine service, medical department, employees (applications, dismissals, promotions salaries); correspondence to and from J.L. Moore, purchasing agent, 1910-1918 (Box 348a)
  - Bills, statements; matters of smoke abatement; scales, buildings, and testing; limestone, ore, coke, and scrap; track matters and repairs; material orders; monthly inventory reports, 1910-1925 (Box 348b)